<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Antidote against some principal errors of the predestinarians a work designed for the information of the common people.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3494A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42462</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36281996</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36281996</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150018</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75470)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2225:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Antidote against some principal errors of the predestinarians a work designed for the information of the common people.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Cumberland ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2]-[4] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dr. Williams' Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANTIDOTE AGAINST <hi>Some Principal Errors</hi> OF THE Predeſtinarians. A Work deſigned for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Common People.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Beloved, believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they are of God; for many falſe Prophets are gone out into the World,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Joh. 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Cumberland</hi> at the Angel in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1696.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:150018:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150018:2"/>
            <head>An <hi>ANTIDOTE</hi> againſt ſome Principal Errors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO convince thoſe of their Miſtake who err in Matters of Religion, is an Act of the greateſt Kindneſs and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that one Man can do unto another: being therefore fully ſatisfied in my ſelf, that ſome of the Predeſtinarian Principles are contrary to Truth. I thought it my Duty to endeavour all that in me lies, to convince them thereof, who ſo believe, by ſhewing that they do not srightly underſtand the true Intent and Meaning of the Word of God; or, that <hi>they err, not knowing the Scriptures,</hi> Mat. 22.29. that is to ſay, not knowing them rightly: for they rely only upon here and there a Place that ſeems to make for them; and in the mean time overlook a far greater Number of Scriptures that very plainly and clearly do teſtify againſt them.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis evident that where one Part of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſeems to declare one thing, and another part ſeems to declare quite the contrary; 'tis evident, I ſay, that there the true ſenſe of one Part is not that which the literal Import of the Words does expreſs: for 'tis certain that two Senſes which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150018:3"/>do oppoſe each other, cannot both be true; in ſuch Caſes then it muſt be that the literal Senſe of one part is the true Senſe, and then the literal Senſe of the other part muſt be myſtical, figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative or alluſive, or ſuch as does ſeem to ſpeak one thing, but does really mean and intend ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Now 'tis not poſſible for any Opinion to be true, that is built on the literal Senſe of ſuch Scriptures as theſe, whoſe right meaning is not that which the Words do at firſt ſight ſeem to expreſs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore before we preſume to make any Text the Foundation of our Faith, we muſt be ſure that the Senſe which we take that Text of Scripture in, is its true and right Senſe. And the way to know this, is to conſider firſt, whether it be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that Senſe which is found to be the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Drift and Scope of the Bible: for we muſt not underſtand any one Scripture in ſuch a Senſe as is contrary to a far greater Number of Places. The general Senſe of the Scriptures is rather to be relied on, than a particular Senſe of only three or four Places. Again, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether the Senſe a Scripture is taken in be agreeable to Reaſon; for no Senſe of Scripture can be true that is contrary to the common and natural Notions of our Minds: for the Law of Nature is as much from God as the Laws of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation are; and 'tis abſurd to think that one part of God's Law can contradict another. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, no Senſe of Scripture can be the true Senſe, if it any ways naturally tend to take Men off
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150018:3"/>from the Care of holy Living, by nouriſhing in them fooliſh Preſumption, or elſe driving of them into miſerable and deep Deſpair.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe few Particulars be well conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they cannot but direct us to the Knowledg of the true and right Senſe of the Scripture: for if any Senſe be the true Senſe, it muſt be that which is agreeable to the greateſt Number Seripture-Teſtimonies, which we have no reaſon to disbelieve, and which has no Tendency in it to favour Wickedneſs, but is every way proper to urge and preſs Mankind to a Life of Piety and Vertue. Now 'tis evident that the Predeſtinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do build many of their Notions on Scriptures taken in that Senſe, which is oppoſite to the Senſe of a far greater Number of Teſtimonies which declare the contrary; and they are alſo taken in ſuch a Senſe as is contrary to all other Evidences of Truth deducible from humane Underſtanding, and which makes many Men falſely conceit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be the Beloved of God, and his Elect, even in the midſt of their Wickedneſs: and that has driven others into Deſpair upon a Suppoſition that they are of that Number whom God, as they think, has eternally reprobated. All which clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove that the Senſe they take theſe Scriptures in, is a Senſe that is not the right and true Senſe; and therefore that Faith is an erroneous Faith which they do build upon it. And this by the Divine Aſſiſtance I will make evident in ſeveral Particulars: And firſt,</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150018:4"/>
               <head>Of REPROBATION.</head>
               <p>The true Subſtance of the Calviniſt Notion concerning Reprobation is, that God has decreed from Eternity to reprobate or torment ſome Men in Hell for ever, that thereby he may make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the Glory of his Juſtice in puniſhing ſome, as well as his Goodneſs in making others hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: and they ſay, that the Number of thoſe who are thus fore-ordained to everlaſting death, is ſo certain, and their Fate is ſo unchangeable upon the Account of this his unalterable Decree, that they can neither be increaſed nor diminiſhed. But this Notion is contrary both to Scripture and Reaſon, and is therefore both a falſe and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Opinion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis contrary to Scripture, I mean ſuch Scriptures as are much more numerous, and more plain and eaſy to be underſtood, than thoſe are upon which this fictionary Faith is founded. <hi>God is Love,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.8. And <hi>in this was his Love manifeſted, in that he ſent his only begotten Son into the World, that we might live through him,</hi> ver. 9. <hi>Say unto them, As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no Pleaſure in the Death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his Way and live: turn ye, turn ye, for why will ye die, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael? Ezek. 33.11. <hi>Have I any Pleaſure at all that the Wicked ſhould die, ſaith the Lord God, and not that he ſhould turn from his Ways and live?</hi> Ezek. 18.23. <hi>I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150018:4"/>have no Pleaſure in the Death of him that dieth, ſaith the Lord God; wherefore turn your ſelves, and live ye,</hi> Ezek. 18.32. Now what can be more abſurd and contrary to Scripture than to aſſert, that he who takes no Pleaſure in the Death of Sinners, ſhould for his own meer Will and Pleaſure, only to ſhew his Power, decree to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and damn the greateſt part of Mankind? If he ſwears that he delights not in their Death, we may depend upon his Word notwithſtanding all the Arguments which the Predeſtinarians can urge to the contrary.</p>
               <p>'Tis likewiſe recorded for a Truth, that <hi>the Lord is good to all, and that his tender Mercies are over all his Works,</hi> Pſal. 145.9. That he <hi>is long-ſuffering to us-ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. That his Will is, that <hi>Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and giving of Thanks be made for all Men—for this is good and acceptable in the Sight of God, who will have all Men to be ſaved, and to come to the Knowledg of the Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.1, 4. And that <hi>the Grace of God that brings Salvation, hath appeared unto all Men,</hi> Tit. 2.11. That <hi>Chriſt is a Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.2. That <hi>he gave himſelf a Ranſon for all,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6. That <hi>he taſted Death for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man,</hi> Heb. 2.9. And that <hi>as by the Offence of one, Judgment came upon all Men to Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; even ſo by the Righteouſneſs of one, the free Gift came upon all Men to Juſtification of Life,</hi> Rom. 5.18.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150018:5"/>
               <p>Now from theſ plain Scriptures 'tis evident, that no particular Man's Damnation is unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly decreed by Go: If Men die the Death eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, their Deſtruction is from themſelves, and not from him. When he made the Generations of Men to dwell upon the Face of the Earth, he made them free Agents, that is to ſay, he gave them a Power either to do, or not to do, what he did intend to command them: but withal he let them know, that if they did diſobey, they ſhould be puniſhed for their ſo doing; and that if they did obey, they ſhould for ever be bleſſed. It was not his purpoſe therefore to damn any Man abſolutely, but conditionally, in caſe he ſhould ſo far abuſe the Powers he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, as wilfully to commit Sin when he might as well have forborn it. Now the Truth of this is evident from many plain and undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Teſtimonies.</p>
               <p>For eternal Puniſhments are only denounc'd againſt Men in Caſe of Wickedneſs. God's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees are, that <hi>the Soul that ſins ſhall die,</hi> Ezek. 18.4. And that <hi>all ſhould be damned who believe not the Truth, but had Pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.12. And that if Men <hi>live after the Fleſh. they ſhall die; but if</hi> on the contrary <hi>they through the Spirit do mortify the Deeds of the Body, they ſhall live,</hi> Rom. 8.13. And therefore he faith, <hi>Whoſoever ſinneth againſt me, him will I blot out of my Book,</hi> Exod. 32.33. By the Sins and Wickedneſſes then which Men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, they make themſelves Reprobates; 'tis <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150018:5"/>of theſe things,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Paul, that the Wrath of God cometh upon the Children of Diſobedience, Eph.</hi> 5.3, 6. God hathſworn that ſome ſhall notenter into his Reſt: <hi>But to whom ſwear he that they ſhould not enter into his Reſt, but to them that believe not?</hi> Heb. 3.18. All which ſhews that God reprobates none but ſuh as by Sin are the Authors of their own Damnation; and therefore 'tis ſaid of the wicked Jews, <hi>O Iſrael, thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf,</hi> Hoſ. 13.9. To ſay therefore that God is the chief, and principal or main Cauſe of Man's eternal Deſtruction, is a Notion you ſee which is contrary to Scripture, and is therefore an Error.</p>
               <p>'Tis alſo an Error, becauſe 'tis built upon ſuch a Senſe of Scripture as we have all the reaſon in the World to disbelieve: for that can never be the true Senſe of God's Word, which naturally tends to debaſe the Glory of the Juſtice and Righteouſneſs of God; but this thoſe Notions do which theſe Men do build on theſe miſtaken Senſes of Scripture: for they tell us, that as God has decreed the End of thoſe whom he has reſolv'd to reprobate, ſo he has alſo decreed the Means which ſhall bring them to that End, that is to ſay, he has decreed that they ſhall una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably be Sinners, that ſo he may manifeſt the Rigour of his Juſtice in puniſhing them for being wicked. But were this true, it would be ſo far from exalting, that it would plainly debaſe the Glory of the Juſtice of God among Men: for according to all the Notions which we have of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150018:6"/>Juſtice, nothing can be more unjuſt and cruel than firſt to lay an unavoidable Neceſſity upon a Man to do ill, that ſo with a ſeeming Juſtice he may be tormented for being wicked. Should one Man do ſo to another, we ſhould count him unjuſt in the higheſt; and <hi>ſhall Man be more juſt than God?</hi> Job 4.17. Then, and then on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the Juſtice of God glorious, when he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes Men for wilfully refuſing to do that which he has made them ſufficiently able by one means or other to perform.</p>
               <p>This Reprobating Notion of theirs, does make the Goſpel a meer piece of Nonſenſe: for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel tells us, <hi>that Repentance and Remiſſion of Sins ſhould be preached in</hi> Chriſt's <hi>Name to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Luke 24.47. And that God does <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all Men every where to repent,</hi> Acts 17.30. But all this the Predeſtinarian Doctrine oppoſes as an impoſſible Thing, a uſeleſs Precept: for it declares that none of them whom God has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to reprobate, can repent, and become good Men; for he has decreed, they ſay, that thoſe Men ſhall be Sinners, that ſo he may bring on them in a way of Juſtice, that eternal Death to which he has foreappointed and deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them: all which, ſay they, no Endeavours sof theirs can prevent; for the moſt profound Repentance which they can perform, will never reverſe what God has thus doom'd them to by an eternal and irreverſible Decree. Which Doctrines are a plain Contradiction to that expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God that all ſhould repent.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150018:6"/>
               <p>They have been alſo the dreadful Occaſion of all that Horror and Deſpair which has been found in a great Number of men who have been afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with doubting and troubled Minds, and has occaſioned others to entertain in themſelves very hard Thoughts of God: for ſuch Notions as theſe do make God ſeem worſe to ſome Men than the Devil; for the Devil they know can force no Man to ſin, he can only tempt, and endeavour to perſwade: but God, according to theſe Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Predeſtinarians, does force and compel Men to ſin by an abſolute Decree, that ſo the Damnation he has deſign'd them to, may appear more Juſt. All which are the occaſion of very hard and evil Thoughts concerning God in thoſe, who under Deſpair are apt to think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the Number of thoſe whom he thus has reprobated: which evil and wicked Surmiſes concerning God had for ever been prevented, had not theſe Doctrines been taught in the World.</p>
               <p>On the contrary 'tis evident beyond Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that the oppoſite Doctrine does much more advance God's Honour, becauſe it teaches that 'tis poſſible for all Men to repent and become good Men: and <hi>herein,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>is my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glorified, that ye bear much Fruit,</hi> John 15.8. It likewiſe tends more to advance the Intereſt of Religion, which conſiſts in every Man's being perſwaded to live a ſober, righteous and godly Life; and it is alſo a Doctrine which is every way more truly conducive to the good of Souls, becauſe it declares that all Men may be happy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150018:7"/>if they will but diligently improve that Talent of Grace that God has given them, in order <hi>to the working out of their own Salvation,</hi> and <hi>the making their own Calling and Election ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis plain to every common Man's Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thoſe Doctrines which teach according to the Scriptures, that God <hi>is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. That he <hi>would have all Men to be ſaved, and come to the Knowledg of the Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4. That <hi>the Manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every Man to profit withal,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. And that by the Improvement of this their Talent they may make themſelves fit to enter into their Maſter's Joy: 'tis evident, I ſay, that ſuch Doctrines as theſe do noways, tend to God's Diſhonour, nor are they iniurious to the true Intereſt of Religion, nor do they any ways endanger the Good of Souls. Nor can any thing be more certain than this, that theſe, and none but theſe Doctrines, can yield true Comfort to them, that on the account of Sin are in Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, becauſe they everywhere and always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it to be the Will of God, that <hi>if the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked will turn away from hsi Wickedneſs that he hath committed: and do that which is lawful and right, he ſhall ſave his Soul alive: all his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions tha he hath committed, they ſhall not be mentioned unto him, in his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs that he hath done he ſhall live,</hi> Ezek. 18.21 to 28.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:150018:7"/>
               <p>Were the Reprobatarian Doctrine true, then all that profeſs it are bound to live up to thoſe Payticulars that are naturally conſequent thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and then it muſt ſollow of courſe, that if all the Actions of Men are fore-determined by God's Decree, and Sin be neceſſitated in ſome, as well as Vertue is in others, that then Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ought not to be look'd upon as more crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in a Reprobate than Thirſt or Hunger: for what is unavoidable, may be a Man's Infelicity in ſome Caſes, but not his Sin; for can it be a Crime in any one to do that which it is the Will of God he ſhall do? If God have decreed from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that ſome Men ſhall ſin unavoidably, that ſo his Deſign of reprobating them may not prove uneffectual; then thoſe that act evil things, are not to be charged with Diſobedience, becauſe they act, ſome ſay, as God deſigns they ſhould act, and by conſequence, according to theſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they are intirely obedient to the Will of their Maker. Wherefore thoſe that pretend to believe theſe Doctrines, ought not to blame and cenſure, and puniſh them for Wickedneſs, but ſay rather, that ſince God has decreed from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity whatſoever ſhall come to paſs in time, that theſe cannot avoid ſo doing; and therefore 'tis the Duty of all to reſt ſatisfied under the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable Execution of the Divine Decrees of God. Now thus to do would be for Men to live up to the Tenure of thoſe Reprobatarian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of eternal Predeſtination which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to believe: but yet we don't ſee this done,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150018:8"/>which ſhews that theſe Dictates of the Spirit of Error are over-powered by thoſe natural Notions of Truth implanted in the Minds of the Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narians. Experience ſhews that they all daily cry out againſt the Wickedneſs of Mankind as a thing unſufferable among humane Beings, and they do all that lies in their Power to bring thoſe to Puniſhment who do ſuch things as are deſtructive to the general or common Good of Men; which ſufficiently demonſtrates, that the Predeſtinarian Faith which they outwardly profeſs, is undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly contrary to that Divine Law which God by Nature has written in the Heart of Man, and for this reaſon theſe Men by their Actions do plainly confute the Faith which they profeſs; for by this they declare unto the World, that they do not believe that Men are wicked by neceſſity from God, for then 'twould be inhumane to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them: but this no Man believes, for they as well as we are verily perſwaded that the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Wicked is juſt and neceſſary, that ſo by their Example others may be deterred from committing the like Crimes; which ſhews that all Men do naturally believe that Sin may be avoided; and if Sin, which is the Cauſe of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, may be avoided, then Damnation, which is only the Effect of Sin, may be avoided too: which proves that the Predeſtinarian Notion of Reprobation is contrary to the natural, as well as to the revealed Law of God, and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to be rejected by all Man, eſpecially by them whoſe Buſineſs it is to perſwade all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150018:8"/>Men <hi>to be reconciled unto God,</hi> which they can never do, unleſs htey declare that 'tis poſſible for all to repent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of ELECTION.</head>
               <p>The Predeſtinarians tell us, that God by an eternal Decree hath elected or choſen to make ſome particular Perſons happy in a Life eternal, and that none ſhall be ſaved but thoſe whom he has thus predeſtinated unto Glory; in which Predeſtination, they ſay no reſpect was had to any Act of Obedience to be perform'd on Man's Part; for according to theſe Men, Obedience is only the fruit of their Election, or what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily does follow thereupon, and not the Means which makes Men fit for Election or Choice of God. But this is an Error, becauſe contrary to plain Scripture, or the revealed Law of our Maker.</p>
               <p>For God has therein fully aſſured us, that our being in favour with him depends upon our doing well, (ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7.) that is to ſay, upon our well uſing thoſe Talents he has entruſted us with, or upon our doing thoſe things that his Word and Law have commanded: and therefore it is that we are bid to <hi>work out our own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Fear and Trembling, for 'tis God that worketh in us to will and to do,</hi> Phil. 2.12. The meaning is, that God has made us capable of doing his Will, in order to make us fit Objects for his Love and Favour; and that therefore we ought to work according as he has enabled us,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150018:9"/>that by ſo doing we may <hi>make our Calling and Election ſure,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10, which will not be, unleſs our own diligent Endeavours do concur with the Aſſiſtance of God: and therefore it is that Men are exhorted <hi>not to receive the Grace of God in vain,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.1.</p>
               <p>'Tis plain that <hi>God is no Reſpecter of Perſons, but that in every Nation he that feareth him, and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted with him,</hi> Acts 10.35. And accordingly a good and vertuous Life is every where made the neceſſary Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Salvation: <hi>Obey my Voice,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>and</hi> then <hi>I will be your God, and ye ſhall be my People,</hi> Jer. 7.23. <hi>If thou wilt enter into Life,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>keep the Commandments,</hi> Mat. 19.17. For as the Pſalmiſt has declared, <hi>He</hi> (that is God) <hi>hath ſet apart the Man that is godly for himſelf,</hi> Pſal. 4.3. In which Words a plain Reaſon is given why God makes one Man happy, and not another, 'tis the Man that is godly that he ſets apart for this Purpoſe. Hence Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>the Author of eternal Salvation to all them that obey him,</hi> Heb. 5.9. 'Tis only by Obedience that we obtain an Intereſt in the ſaving Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt; and accordingly his Goſpel does declare, that <hi>if through the Spirit</hi> (which is given to every Man to profit withal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.) <hi>we do mortify the Deeds of the Body, we ſhall live,</hi> Rom. 8.13. <hi>If a Man purge himſelf from theſe, he ſhall be a Veſſel unto Honour, ſanctified and meet for the Maſter's uſe,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.21.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150018:9"/>
               <p>Thus 'tis evident, that in God's Chooſing or Electing he only has reſpect to them, who by the due Uſe and Improvement of their common Talent, have made themſelves fit for thoſe Joys which he has promiſed to them that will heartily and ſincerely ſerve him; the Favours of Election or Chooſing to the Happineſs of Salvation, are conferr'd on none but thoſe that <hi>have a Right to the Tree of Life,</hi> Rev. 22.14. by Virtue of thoſe Conditional Promiſes which God out of his free Grace and Mercy has made to Men. <hi>His Mercy is only on them that fear him throughout all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations,</hi> Luke 1.50. <hi>If we confeſs our Sins</hi> (ſo as to forſake them) <hi>he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our Sins,</hi> (according to his Promiſe) <hi>and to cleanſe us from all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.9. Hence 'tis plain that all the well-grounded Hope that Men can have in God's Mercy, does wholly depend upon the Aſſurance of their hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the utmoſt of their Power performed thoſe Conditions, upon the Performance of which God has promiſed to be merciful to Mankind.</p>
               <p>It plainly appears from the moſt general Scope of the Scriptures, that <hi>God in his Electing and Chuſing is no Reſpecter of Perſons, but of Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations:</hi> neither does he reprobate any Man meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he will do ſo, but becauſe they do wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully commit Sin and Wickedneſs. That God decrees to elect ſome, and reprobate others, is a moſt undoubted Truth; and theſe his Decrees are unalterable in themſelves, but yet conditional in reſpect of them on whom they take place, it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150018:10"/>being the ſtanding Law of Heaven, that <hi>if Men live after the Felſh, they ſhall die,</hi> or that Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhall be inflicted in caſe Men will commit Sin; <hi>but if through the Spirit they mortify the Deeds of the Body, they ſhall live,</hi> Rom. 8.13. Here the Terms and Conditions of Happineſs or Miſery are plainly expreſt; theſe are the Reaſons of God's different way of dealing with Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; 'tis for this Reaſon that he loves one Man, and hates another, that is to ſay, he always loves good Men, and hates the Wicked, <hi>If thou doſt well,</hi> ſaith he to <hi>Cain, ſhalt thou not be accepted? and if thou doſt not well, Sin lieth at thy Door,</hi> Gen. 4.7. Theſe things well conſidered, are a clear Proof that the Calviniſt Notion concerning Election is an Error, and that the contrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is the undoubted Truth of God.</p>
               <p>For certain I am, that no Man can prove it a Diſhonour to God, to ſay, that in his Electing or Chooſing he does not reſpect the meer Perſon of any Man, but the fitneſs or <hi>meetneſs of Men for the Maſter's <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> and that <hi>in every Nation he that feareth God and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted with him:</hi> or that <hi>he ſets apart the Man that is Godly for himſelf.</hi> Neither is the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Religion any ways hindred by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that God <hi>would have all Men to be ſaved, and come to the Knowledg of the Truth;</hi> and that all Men may be ſaved, if they will but <hi>give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to make their own Calling and Election ſure,</hi> and be careful <hi>not to grieve the Holy Spirit;</hi> or in other Words, <hi>not to receive the Grace of God in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150018:10"/>vain.</hi> Nor can it be any ways injurious to the Good of Souls to tell Men, as Chriſt hath done, that <hi>if they will enter into Life, they muſt keep the Commandments:</hi> and that <hi>God commands all Men every where to repent;</hi> and having repented, to be ſtedfaſt and unmoveable in their Reſolutions of keeping God's Commands for the future; and that they ſtudy how to abound more and more in the Work of the Lord, <hi>foraſmuch as they know that their Labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.58.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine is much more ſutable to the great End and Deſign of the Goſpel (which was to advance among Men the Practice of true Piety and Godlineſs) than the contrary Doctrine, which teaches that Vertue and Piety do not recommend us to God, who 'tis ſaid does firſt decree to ſave, and then does irreſiſtibly ſanctify; Righteouſneſs not being, as the Predeſtinarians ſay, the Means of Mens being elected or choſen, but that Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the Means or Cauſe of their being made righteous by God. If Men are elected, ſay they, God will then ſanctify them without their own Endeavours, that ſo the Glory thereof may redound wholly to himſelf; which they think could not be, ſhould God make Men capable of doing any thing towards the ſaving of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>So that the Reſult of this Opinion is, tht if God have elected any Man, he ſhall (but not by any Endeavour of his own) be made a good Man before he dies; and that if he be not elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150018:11"/>all the Endeavours he can uſe ſhall never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe that Decree, to the ſaving of his Soul: which plainly is no other than a Doctrine proper to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage a licentious Careleſneſs in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of unthinking Men, and take others off from that holy Care and Caution which is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to the Attainment of Life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: and doubtleſs this is that which encourages the looſer Sort who are of this Perſwaſion, to do many unjuſtifiable things, upon Preſumption that no Sin can damn the Elect. And 'tis worth obſerving here, that all do think themſelves among the Number of the Elect, that do believe this Doctrine; and this makes great Numbers of them ſo remiſs and careleſs as they are, for they are perſwaded that before they die God will ſome way or other without their own Endeavours ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtibly ſanctify them: hence it is that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them go on with ſo much Confidence and Comfort in a Courſe of Wickedneſs, than which nothing can be more unſafe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Redemption.</head>
               <p>The Predeſtinarians teach, that as God did not intend the Salvation of all Men, ſo neither did Chriſt die for all, ſo as to put all Men into a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of obtaining Life eternal: but this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is contrary to Scripture, and for that Reaſon is undoubtedly falſe.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150018:11"/>
               <p>The Scripture tells us plainly that the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Jeſus Chriſt was univerſal, that <hi>he gave his Life a Ranſom for all,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6. that <hi>by the Grace of God he taſted Death for every Man,</hi> Heb. 2.9. that <hi>he is the Propitiation for the Sins of the whole World,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.2. that <hi>as in</hi> Adam <hi>all die, even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.22. that <hi>as by the Offence of one Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came upon all Men to Condemnation, ſo by the Righteouſneſs of one the free Gift came upon all Men to Juſtification of Life,</hi> Rom. 5.18. And 'tis evident that the Deſign of God in his ſending of Chriſt was the Salvation of all; for <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, that whoſoever believed in him, ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting Life,</hi> Joh. 3.16. and therefore 'tis ſaid that <hi>to every one is given Grace, according to the Meaſure of the Gift of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4.7. and that <hi>the Grace of God that brings Salvation, hath appeared unto all Men,</hi> Tit. 2.11. that <hi>he is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. that <hi>he would have all Men to be ſaved, and come to the Knowledg of the Truth,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this we find the Angel thus ſpeaking to the Shepherds, <hi>Fear not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for behold I bring you good Tidings of great Joy, which ſhall be unto all People; for unto you is born this Day in the City of</hi> David, <hi>a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord,</hi> Luke 2.10, 11. And the Pſalmiſt tells us, that <hi>the Lord is good to all, and his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150018:12"/>tender Mercies are over all his Works,</hi> pſal. 145.9. For which Reaſon he proclaims himſelf to be <hi>the Lord God, merciful and gracious, long ſuffering, and abundant in Goodneſs and Truth,</hi> Exod. 34.6. Which univerſal Declarations of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs do make it moſt evident, that the ſaving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of God in Jeſus Chriſt were extended to the whole World, God having thereby put all Men into a Capacity of being made Happy, if they will but do on their Part what he has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and what he for the Sake of Chriſt has made them able to perform; and none can miſs of Salvation but by their own wilful Neglect: If <hi>they will not come to Chriſt that they may have Life,</hi> the Fault is their own: <hi>How ſhall we eſcape,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>if we neglect ſo great Salvation?</hi> Heb. 2.3.</p>
               <p>Some I know are ſo ſenſleſs as to imagin that their Notion of particular Grace does magnify, and more exalt the Glory of God's free Grace, than it would be exalted, were the free Grace of God univerſally extended to all Men. But the Reaſon of every common Man will ſerve to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute this; for every one knows that he who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes towards the making a thouſand Perſons happy, is much more good and gracious than he who is kind only to two or three: the Grace of God is never a whit the leſs free for its being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended unto all; but as for the Riches of the free Grace of God there's no Compariſon to be made between that which is general and which is particular; for the more univerſally the Grace is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150018:12"/>extended, the more rich in all Reſpects it is: which ſhews that the Predeſtinarian Notion of God's intending to be gracious, through Jeſus Chriſt, but to a few Men, to the utter Excluſion of all the reſt, does but tend to eclipſe the Glory of the free and undeſerved Grace of God; and that which does ſo, muſt needs be an Error.</p>
               <p>'Tis evident likewiſe that this Doctrine is an Error, from the Practice of thoſe Preachers that profeſs it; for they often declare <hi>that God hath committed unto them the Word of Reconciliation, and therefore as Ambaſſadors for Chriſt they pray the People in Chriſt's ſtead to be reconciled unto God, that ſo their former Treſpaſſes may not be imputed unto them,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.18, 19, 20. For, ſay they, as God has <hi>commanded all Men every where to repent,</hi> Acts 17.30. ſo we have a Commiſſion <hi>to preach Repentance and Remiſſion of Sins to all Nations</hi> in the Name of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. but at the ſame time you never hear them ſay, Beloved, don't think that by this we preach that curſed Doctrine of Univerſal Redemption by Chriſt, as if by what he has done for Mankind all were put into a new Capacity of obtaining Life eternal: no, we declare the contrary, that tho by us <hi>God does command all Men every where to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> yet by his eternal Decree he has made it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for all thoſe to repent which are not firſt elected: we may exhort you all to repent indeed, becauſe we don't know who are elected, and who are not; but if there be none of the Elect among
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150018:13"/>you, our Exhortations will all be in vain; for the Non-elect cannot <hi>come to Chriſt, that they may have Life,</hi> tho he bids <hi>all come that are weary and heavy-laden, that they may find Reſt to their Souls,</hi> Mat. 11.29. No Man, I ſay, ever heard a Predeſtinarian Preacher ſpeak thus; but thus they ought to ſpeak, were their Practice an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the Principles which they hold: but their not doing ſo evidently ſhews that this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is repugnant to the true Office and Duty of a Miniſter, and for that very Reaſon ought by all Men to be rejected as an Error.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of FREE-WILL.</head>
               <p>The Predeſtinarians teach that God has not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto Man ſuch a Freedom and Power of Will, as does enable him either to do or not to do what he requires of him: for they ſay, that as one part of Men are reprobated, and the other are elected, ſo he will unavoidably make them righteous whom he decrees to ſave, and as unavoidably make them wicked whom he decrees to damn; for as God has decreed the End of Men, whether it be Salvation or Damnation, ſo he has decreed the Means that ſhall bring them thereunto: theſe things, ſay they, are not left to their own Choice, neither is it in their own Power to be that which God has not abſolutely determined them to. But this Notion is contrary alſo to Scripture and Reaſon, and is therefore an Error.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150018:13"/>
               <p>The general Importance of the Scriptures does make it evident, that Man is a Being to whom God has given ſuch Powers as do ſufficiently enable him either to do the Will of God, or elſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey it: and therefore we are exhorted to <hi>give all Diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10. and to <hi>work out our Salvation with fear and trembling,</hi> Phil. 2.12. and to <hi>labour to enter into that Reſt,</hi> Heb. 4.11. and to <hi>cleanſe our ſelves from all Filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.1. and to <hi>caſt away from us all our Tranſgreſſions, and make us new Hearts and new Spirits,</hi> Ezek. 18.31. And to the ſame purpoſe St. <hi>James</hi> preſſes thoſe to whom he wrote, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Cleanſe your Hands ye Sinners, and purify your Hearts ye double-minded,</hi> Jam. 4.8. All which do clearly imply that God has given Men a Power to do his Will, elſe he would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort them to do it as we ſee he has done; and if he exhorts all Men to do this, and yet they all do not do it, as we ſee they do not, this is a plain Proof on the other hand, that they have a Power to diſobey.</p>
               <p>And indeed the Divine Law of God is a clear and demonſtrative Proof that the Will of Man is free; for it would be in vain to oblige Men by a Law to do one thing, and not to do another, if there were a natural Neceſſity that Men muſt do theſe things. As there is no place then, ſo neither is there any need of an Obligation, where there is no Liberty nor Power of Choice; but where Beings have a Power to act two different
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150018:14"/>ways, in ſuch a Caſe it is proper to give ſuch Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings a Law to tie them up, or oblige them to act only one way: and for this Reaſon it is that among all the Creatures found in this lower World, Men alone are bound to the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Laws, becauſe no Creature beſide is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with Freedom of Will, and Liberty of Choice.</p>
               <p>Nothing doubtleſs can be more unreaſonable than to believe that God ſhould give a Law to Mankind, and expreſly promiſe Rewards to them that will obey on the one hand, and on the other hand threaten Puniſhments to them that diſobey, and yet believe withal, that he has eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally decreed whatſoever ſhall come to paſs, ſo that it is not in the Power either of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous or the Wicked to do otherwiſe than we ſee they do; or in other Words, that it is not in the Power of ſome to diſobey ſo far as to damn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor in the Power of others to obey ſo far as is effectual for Salvation: for were it ſo that Men had no liberty or freedom of Choice in theſe Matters, there then would need no Law to forbid Men to do what is impoſſible they ſhould do, or command the doing of that, which they unavoidably muſt do. Wherefore God's giving unto Man a Law, is a plain Demonſtration that there is in him a Freedom of Will.</p>
               <p>Hence the Lord God thus ſpeaks unto <hi>Iſrael, See, I have ſet before thee Life and Death, Good and Evil. In that I command thee this Day to love the Lord thy God, to walk in his Ways, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150018:14"/>to keep his Commandments, and his Statutes, and his Judgments, that thou mayeſt live—but if thine Heart turn away, ſo that thou wilt not bear—I do denounce unto you this Day, that ye ſhall ſurely periſh.</hi> And he adds—<hi>I have ſet before you Life and Death, Bleſſing and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; therefore chuſe Life, that both thou and thy Seed may live,</hi> Deut. 30.15, 16, 17, 18, 19. From which Words we may infer ſafely, that God has laid upon Man no abſolute Neceſſity of being either happy or miſerable, but <hi>he deals with them as with Perſons who have from him a Power to obey or diſobey, as themſelves</hi> (by the Power of thoſe Faculties they have from him) <hi>do beſt pleaſe:</hi> only he tells them what the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces either of Obedience or Diſobedience will be, that Life ſhall be the Reward of the one, and Death of the other; and withal, that <hi>his Deſire and Will is that they ſhould chooſe Life, and not Death.</hi> The Words of <hi>David</hi> unto <hi>Solomon</hi> do alſo plainly imply this free Agency of Man; <hi>And thou</hi> Solomon <hi>my Son,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>know thou the God of thy Father, and ſerve him with a perfect Heart, and willing Mind— If thou ſeek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for ever,</hi> 1 Chron. 28.9. as do likewiſe the Words of the Prophet <hi>Azariah</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Aſa; And he ſaid unto him, Hear ye me,</hi> Aſa, <hi>and all</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Benjamin, <hi>The Lord is with you, while ye be with him; and if ye ſeek him, he will be found of you; but if ye forſake him, he will forſake you,</hi> 2 Chron. 15.2.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150018:15"/>
               <p>And we find accordingly that the Scriptures do moſt abundantly declare that both Vertue and Vice are the Effect of our own free Choice: and for this Reaſon we are commanded <hi>not to envy the Oppreſſor, and that we ſhould chooſe none of his ways,</hi> Prov. 3.31. And therefore <hi>Mary</hi> is ſaid to have <hi>choſen the good Part, which ſhould never be taken from her,</hi> Luke 10.42. And it is alſo written, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord unto the Eunuchs, that—chooſe the things that pleaſe me—I will give them an everlaſting Name,</hi> Iſa. 56.4, 5. On the other hand it is ſaid, <hi>They did Evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine Eyes, and chòſe that wherein I delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not,</hi> Iſa. 65.12. <hi>They have choſen their own Ways, and their Soul delighteth in their Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Iſa. 66.3. <hi>Ye will not come to me, that ye might have Life,</hi> Joh. 5.40. <hi>My People would not hearken unto my Voice, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>would none of me; ſo I gave them up to their own Hearts Luſt,</hi> Pſal. 81.11, 12. <hi>They would none of my Counſel, they deſpiſed all my Reproof,</hi> Prov. 1.30. <hi>O</hi> Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, <hi>how often would I have gathered thee as an Hen gathereth her Chickens, and ye would not?</hi> Mat. 23.37. All which wholly lays the Guilt. of Sin upon the Sinner's Wilfulneſs; they choſe to do ill, when they might have choſen to do well, as others did by virtue of thoſe Powers which God had given them.</p>
               <p>Hence 'tis ſaid that <hi>to whom ye yield your ſelves Servants to obey, his Servants ye are to whom ye obey, whether it be of Sin unto Death, or of Obedience unto Righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 6.16. Which plainly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150018:15"/>implies that 'tis our own voluntary Act that makes us Servants either to God or the Devil: as for God 'tis plain that he neceſſitates no Man to ſerve him; he gives to all Men a Power to obey his Will, but he will not force them to obey whether they will or no; he could force them to do ſo if he pleaſed, but his infinite Wiſdom does not think it fit: yea, <hi>ſhould he do ſo, he would then deprive them of the Advantage of thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards which his Goodneſs has been pleaſed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to that true Love, which only can be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by a free and unconſtrained Obedience.</hi> But as for the Devil, his Power does not extend ſo far as to force any Man to do wickedly; he can tempt indeed, but he cannot neceſſitate: for <hi>God is faithful, and will not ſuffer you to be tempted above what you are able,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.13. Do but <hi>reſiſt him</hi> with that Ability that God has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee, and <hi>he will fly from thee,</hi> Jam. 4.7. Men do not ſin for want of Power to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but becauſe they will not uſe the Power that God has given them. If God will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer us to be tempted above what we are able, then 'tis our willingly yielding to the Devil when we had Power to reſiſt, that makes us the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Slaves of Sin.</p>
               <p>'Tis manifeſt that every Man has a Power to do that which God has made him able to do; and God does not require more of any Man. <hi>If there be a willing Mind,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>it is accepted according to what a Man hath, and not according to what he hath not,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.12.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150018:16"/>He that improved his two Talents was kindly accepted, as well as he that did improve his five Talents; ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. Be ſure to make the beſt Uſe that thou canſt of the Powers that thou haſt; and then if thy preſent Powers are not ſufficient to enable thee to make thy own Calling and Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure, God will not ſail at laſt to give thee that Power that is ſufficient: for he has made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe unto Men by the Mouth of our Bleſſed Lord, that more Grace ſhall be given to them that make a good Uſe of the Grace they have; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto every one that hath ſhall be given,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and he ſhall have abundance; but from him that hath not, ſhall be taken away even that which he hath:</hi> See <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29.</p>
               <p>If the general Current of the Scriptures be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, it will appear evident, that if Men make that uſe they ought of the Talent of Common Grace, or thoſe general Indowments of Reaſon and Humanity, which all but Idiots do receive in ſome Meaſure from the Bounty and Goodneſs of God to them, he will be merciful in a greater Meaſure, by giving them ſuch other Graces as ſhall fully enable them <hi>to work out their own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> but from them that will not make that uſe they ought of Common Grace, he will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his Special Grace, or that Grace that is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. And in ſo doing God is not to be blamed: <hi>For why ſhould the true Riches be committed to his Truſt, that already has made a wrong <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the unrighteous Mammon?</hi> Hence then 'tis evident, that by nature, which is from God, Men are able
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150018:16"/>to do that, which God has promiſed to bleſs with ſaving or ſupernatural Grace or Power.</p>
               <p>There is, I know, a great Out-cry made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Doctrine of Free-will, as if the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which aſſerts that Men have a Power from God, either to do or diſobey his Will, were diſhonourable to God, and did make Man's Strength greater than that of his Maker. But why ſhould it be diſhonourable to God to make Man a free Agent? All confeſs he made <hi>Adam</hi> ſo, and why ſhould it be a Diſhonour to him to ſay he has made us ſo too? As he certainly has, for we have as full a Power now to obey or not obey the Law of the ſecond Covenant, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires only Sincerity, as <hi>Adam</hi> had to obey or diſobey the firſt Covenant, which did require ſinleſs Obedience: and as for the Diſhonour which ſome think is reflected on God, by ſaying that his Creatures have an Ability to diſobey his Will, it will all vaniſh, if we conſider that he may ſuffer this if he pleaſes, ſince he has a Right to do what he will with his own; and beſides, the Superiority of his Power above Man's Power will ſufficiently appear at length in that ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Puniſhment which he will eternally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict on them that diſobey. He may ſuffer Men <hi>to walk in their own Ways,</hi> Acts 14.16. <hi>that he may prove them,</hi> as he did <hi>Iſrael, to know what is in their Heart; that he may do them good at their latter End:</hi> ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.2, 16. But they will have but little Cauſe to brag of their being able to reſiſt him in this the time of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150018:17"/>when for their ſo doing they ſhall be condemned to <hi>dwell in everlaſting Burnings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From what has been ſaid hitherto, I think it is evident, that 'tis in every Man's Power to be as good, as the Uſe of thoſe Natural Endowments which God has beſtowed on every reaſonable Man will admit of: for by the Uſe of the natural Endowment of five Talents, he may attain to eminent Degrees of Vertue and Perfection; and by the Uſe of the natural Endowment of two Talents, he may ſo far expreſs Eaithfulneſs in the Truſt committed to him, as to obtain the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a ſaving Reward from his Lord, tho in an inferiour Degreee: for as the common Gifts of Men differ, ſo will the Rewards promiſed be Proportional only to the Improvement, which the Gift they have does enable them to make: He that well improved his five Talents, was made Ruler over five Cities; and he that improved the two that were given him, was made Ruler over two Cities; and he that had one Talent given him, would have been made Ruler over one City, had he improved it as the others did. Hence the Reaſon of the different Degrees of Vertue among very good Men is evident. <hi>Who maketh thee to differ?</hi> is a Scripture-queſtion. I anſwer, 'tis God that makes Men to differ, ſince that by Nature he endows one Man with better Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties than another: but no Man has reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of this, ſo long as he gives to every Man as much as will intitle him to an Intereſt in his ſaving Grace, if he improve it, as the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150018:17"/>Gift it ſelf does enable him to do.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe evident from what has been ſaid, that 'tis in every Man's Power to be wicked ſo far as to be worthy of Damnation, tho ſome have not abilities ſufficient to be as wicked as others are: for as the Degrees of Vertue in Men are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by the preventing Grace of God, ſo alſo the Degrees of Vice in Men are limited by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining Grace; and as a Man can't be better than the utmoſt Improvement of that Talent will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of which is given him, ſo neither can he be more wicked than the reſtraining Grace of God will permit or ſuffer. But yet after all there is no neceſſity laid upon Man by God to be as bad as he can be; neither has he laid upon Man a Neceſſity of being as good as he may be: theſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to his own Choice, and that Freedom of Will with which his moſt wiſe Creator has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed him. And of the Truth of this almoſt every one's Experience and Conſcience may fully convince him: for I believe there are very few who will be ſo diſingenuous as to affirm, that it was not any-ways poſſible for them to have lived better and more holily than they have done, nor that it was impoſſible for them to have forborn any of thoſe evil things which they know they have committed.</p>
               <p>I will conclude this Head, by only asking the Predeſtinarians this Queſtion; Suppoſe all Men ſhould believe (as they may do if they will) that God has given them a Power <hi>to work out their own Salvation,</hi> provided they do work
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150018:18"/>while an Opportunity to work is given them, that is to ſay in the preſent time, or <hi>to Day,</hi> for to Morrow their Lives may be taken away, and then all Opportunity is for ever at an end: ſhould all, I ſay, believe this, and ſhould all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Importance of this their Belief repent truly of their Sins, and by God's Grace become holy, juſt and ſober Men; what hurt would accrue hereby either to the Glory of God, the Intereſt of Religion, or the Good of Souls? yea, they themſelves cannot preſs Men to the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Repentance and Holineſs, without teaching the very Principles of them that do believe that the Will is free.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Falling from Grace.</head>
               <p>The Predeſtinarian Doctrine in this Point is, that a Man who is once in a State of ſaving Grace, can never fall from it, or can never be in danger of Damnation by any Act of Sin which he ſhall afterwards commit: but this is an Error, becauſe 'tis contrary to Scripture, which not only fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warns Men of the Danger, but declares expreſly, that righteous Men may become wicked, and die in Sin; and 'tis alſo a Doctrine proper to give Men Peace and Comfort in a Courſe of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and for that Reaſon ought to be rejected by all good Men.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place then, the Scripture plainly forewarns good Men of the Danger; which ſhews that 'tis poſſible for good Men to fall from a State
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150018:18"/>of ſaving Grace. <hi>Beware,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>leſt ye alſo being led away with the Error of the Wicked, fall from your own Stedfaſtneſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.17. <hi>Let us not be weary in well-doing; for in due time we ſhall reap if we faint not,</hi> Gal. 6.9. <hi>And you that were alienated, and Enemies in your Minds by wicked Works, yet now hath he reconciled—to preſent you blameleſs, if ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Faith, grounded and ſettled, and be not moved away from the Hope of the Goſpel,</hi> Col. 1.21, 22, 23. <hi>If a Man abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a Branch, and is withered,</hi> Joh. 15.6. <hi>Now the Juſt ſhall live by Faith; but if any Man draw back, my Soul ſhall have no Pleaſure in him,</hi> Heb. 10.38. <hi>Let him therefore that thinks he ſtandeth</hi> (ſo faſt as that no Sin ſhall move him) <hi>take heed leſt he fall,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.12. <hi>Ye did run well,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians, who did hinder you that ye ſhould not obey the Truth?</hi> Gal. 5.7.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Scripture expreſly declares, that righteous Men may become wicked, and die in their Sins: for 'tis ſaid thus, that <hi>when the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous turneth away from his Righteouſneſs, and committeth Iniquity—ſhall he live? all the Righteouſneſs he hath done, ſhall not be mentioned; in his Treſpaſs that he hath treſpaſſed, and in his Sin that he hath ſinned, in them he ſhall die,</hi> Ezek. 18.24. <hi>When a righteous Man turneth away from his Righteouſneſs, and committeth Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and dieth in them, for his Iniquity that he hath done he ſhall die,</hi> Ezek. 18.26. And agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150018:19"/>hereunto are the Words of <hi>David</hi> to his Son <hi>Solomon; And thou</hi> Solomon <hi>my Son,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>know thou the God of thy Father, and ſerve him with a perfect Heart, and with a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Mind: if thou ſeek him, he will be found of thee; but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for ever,</hi> 1 Chron. 28.9. <hi>It is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> ſaith the Author to the Hebrews, <hi>for thoſe who were once enlightned, and have taſted of the Heavenly Gift, and were made Partakers of the holy Ghoſt, and the Powers of the World to come, if they ſhall fall away, to renew them again to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> Heb. 6.4, 5, 6. Hence 'tis ſaid of the younger Widows that were wanton, that they <hi>have Damnation, becauſe they have caſt off their firſt Faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.12.</p>
               <p>Now theſe and ſuch-like Scripture-Evidences are a plain and undeniable Proof that righteous Men may fall from a State of Salvation, and die in their Sins; and therefore the Doctrine which aſſerts the contrary, is certainly an Error.</p>
               <p>Yea, 'tis a foul Error, becauſe it gives En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Sin and Wickedneſs, ſince it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts that no Sin can provoke God to withdraw his ſaving Grace from them that are once Saints: but ſuch Preſumption has doubtleſs ruined more Souls than deep Deſpair; for how are bad Men (as there are many of this Perſwaſion as well as of others) hereby encouraged to do ill things, when they ſhall be perſwaded that no Sin can deprive them of God's Favour who are once
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150018:19"/>inroll'd in the Book of Life? And 'tis evident that the Generality of both Good and Bad who believe this Doctrine, are ſo fooliſh as to think that they are all certainly of this Number, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe they profeſs themſelves Predeſtinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and therefore they comfort up themſelves with this Conſideration, that tho they are guilty of ſome groſs Sins, yet their Salvation is ſtill ſafe, becauſe their Names are written, as they think, in the Book of Life: than which no Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in the World can be more proper to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Wickedneſs, nor can any thing be more contrary to Scripture, which expreſly affirms thus, <hi>Whoſoever ſinneth againſt me, him will I blot out of my Book,</hi> Exod. 32.33. Which ſhews that a Man may be in God's Book, and yet he may afterwards commit ſuch Sins as ſhall blot him out of it.</p>
               <p>'Tis not to be ſuppoſed that Men will much boggle at any Matter of worldly Advantage, when they are really perſwaded that good Works are not concern'd in Juſtification: for they think that Juſtification is only the Fruit of Election, and not the Fruit of Obedience to God's Law; and that being elected, they are by Conſequence juſtified before they are ſanctified, or in a State of Grace before they are converted unto God; none being converted, they ſay, but thoſe who are before in God's Love, by virtue of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of eternal Election; and that after Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which does only manifeſt their being elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if they do happen to ſin, and fall very
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150018:20"/>foully, as <hi>David</hi> did, yet God ſtill loves them as much under this their Relapſe as he did before their firſt Converſion: and tho ſuch Sins may bring upon them temporal Miſeries, yet they ſhall never deprive them of eternal Glory; for they ſhall not die, till by an unreſiſtible Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er God has raiſed them up again by Repentance. They confeſs they may fall for a time, but their Fall ſhall not be final, nor end in Death eternal.</p>
               <p>Men, I ſay, that believe all this, and believe withal that they themſelves are of the Number of theſe elected Ones, as great Numbers do who have no other ground for their ſo doing but Self-confidence, and an erroneous Perſwaſion that ſo it is; theſe, I ſay, have a great deal of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement not to boggle at ſuch Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Actions, as others who really believe the contrary, dare not either take or do, for fear leſt God ſhould cut them off in their Sins, and damn their Souls; 'tis plain that ſuch have not thoſe Advantages of doing ill afforded them from their Faith as the others have, becauſe they dare not do an ill thing, leſt they ſhould loſe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God: they may ſin by ſurpriſe, but they dare not ſin preſumptuouſly. But the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that there's no eternal Danger in it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe whom God once loves, he loves to the end; and he will not ſo ſee Sin in his Elect as to damn them for it: and this they call a Doctrine full of Comfort and Conſolation; and indeed it does in this reſpect equal that of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150018:20"/>Papiſt; for as a Papiſt's Sins do not much terrify him, becauſe he believes the Prieſt can forgive him upon Confeſſion, ſo neither can the other's, becauſe he believes God will not take away his Life till he has brought him to Repentance.</p>
               <p>That there are wicked Men among thoſe who believe contrary to theſe Predeſtinarian Doctrines, I readily grant: but they have no Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be wicked from any natural Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that may be drawn from the Doctrines they believe; they are plainly ſelf-condemned by their own Principles in all the Evils which they do allow themſelves in Some, I know, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perſwade the World that the Doctrine of Free-Will does encourage Men to Wickedneſs, becauſe they ſay it makes many think that if God has given Men a Power to repent when they will, that therefore they may ſin as long as they pleaſe, and repent at laſt: but in this they are ſtrangely miſtaken; for tho we teach that Men who have not hardned their own Hearts by many repeated Acts of wilful and malicious sins againſt God, may repent if they pleaſe at any time, yet we don't teach that Men can live as long as they pleaſe; and we know that when Life ceaſes, then the Opportunity. of Repentance ceaſes alſo. God that promiſes Pardon whenever we ſincerely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, has not promiſed us a <hi>To morrow</hi> to repent in; and no Man who rightly believes that there is in Man a Free-Will, will be ſo mad to ſay, I will yet ſin on one Week longer, and then repent, when for ought he knows his Death
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150018:21"/>may come this very Day, and prevent his ſo repenting.</p>
               <p>Thus 'tis plain that no Free-willer, who tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtands the Nature of the Doctrine which he profeſſes, can ſin without being ſenſible of the Danger of Damnation; whereas the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Perſwaſion plainly infers, that Diſobedience can never make void the Decree of God to ſave them that are elect, or in a State of Salvation, even in ſpite of their own reſiſtance: ſo that 'tis evident a Predeſtinarian may ſin with ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and Comfort, but the Free-willer always ſins under great Diſcouragement from his own Principles, there being in his Faith nothing that can yield him any Security in his ſo doing. I will conclude this Point by asking the Predeſtinarians this one Queſtion, as I before have done under ſome of the other Heads; Suppoſe all Mankind that believe the Goſpel, and endeavour to live up to it, ſhould be perſwaded that 'tis poſſible for thoſe that are in a State of ſaving Grace to fall from it, and ſhould they by virtue of this Perſwaſion be careful, through the Divine Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>not to fall from their own Stedfaſtneſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 17. nor <hi>fail of the Grace of God,</hi> Heb. 12.15. and ſo live good and pious Lives; what hurt would this do either to the Intereſt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or the Good of Souls? Where is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety or Perniciouſneſs of ſuch a Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that the Predeſtinarians ſhould ſo long and ſo loudly exclaim againſt it? I am ſure 'tis a Faith that all truly good Men practiſe, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150018:21"/>which he Adverſaries do themſelves teach in all their Exhortations to a vertuous and godly Way of living.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Period of Humane Life.</head>
               <p>The Predeſtinarians teach likewiſe, that the Period of humane Life is unchangeably fixt by God, ſo that no Man can either live longer, or die ſooner than he does: but this is alſo an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural Doctrine, as well as unreaſonable, and therefore an Error.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures do plainly imply that by Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs Men may cut their Lives ſhort, and that by Righteouſneſs Mens Lives may be prolonged. Thus 'tis ſaid, <hi>The Fear of the Lord prolongeth Days; but the Years of the Wicked ſhall be ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> Prov. 10.27. Again, <hi>as Righteouſneſs ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to Life, ſo he that purſueth Evil, purſueth it to his own Death,</hi> Prov. 11.19. Again, 'tis ſaid, <hi>Evil Doers ſhall be cut off; but thoſe that wait upon the Lord, they ſhall inherit the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 37.9. Beſides theſe Teſtimonies, 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that in many Places of Scripture Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is threatned with a ſhort Life: thus 'tis ſaid, <hi>Bloody and deceitful Men ſhall not live out half their Days,</hi> Pſal. 55.28. <hi>Be not overmuch wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, neither be thou fooliſh; for why ſhould'ſt thou die before thy time?</hi> Eccleſ. 7.17. LOng Life is alſo promiſed to Goodneſs and Vertue, as thus: <hi>My Son, forget nto my Law, but let thine Heart keep my Commandments: for length of Days
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150018:22"/>and long Life and Peace ſhall they add unto thee,</hi> Prov. 3.1, 2. <hi>Becauſe he hath ſet his Love upon me, therefore I will deliver him—with long Life will I ſatisfy him, and ſhew him my Salvation,</hi> Pſal. 91.14, 16. <hi>Happy is the Man that findeth Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Man that getteth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding—ſhe is more precious than Rubies; and all things that thou canſt deſire are not to be compared unto her: length of Days is in her right Hand, and in her left Hand Riches and Honour,</hi> Prov. 3.13, 15, 16. <hi>Hear, O my Son, and receive my Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and the Years of thy Life ſhall be many,</hi> Prov. 4.10. <hi>Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy Days may be long in the Land,</hi> Exod. 20.12. Thus you ſee the Scriptures do plainly confute this fooliſh Notion.</p>
               <p>And as the Scriptures confute it, ſo the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Voice of Nature is againſt it, or that which we call the Law of Self-preſervation; and indeed 'twould be utterly in vain to make Laws to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh common Murders, yea and King-killers too, with Death, if 'twere not poſſible for thoſe that are ſo killed to live any longer: and to ſay that a Man that is executed upon a Gibbet for any Crime, ſhould have died that very Moment, had he not done thoſe things that brought him to the Gallows, is perfect Nonſenſe; and yet this muſt have been, if the Period of every Man's Life were ſo irrevocably fix'd, that he could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther live longer nor die ſooner than he does. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, this Doctrine has been of pernicious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to many, who in Sickneſs out of a falſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150018:22"/>Perſwaſion that they ſhould not die before their time, as they call it, have neglected to ſeek the Means which by God are appointed to heal the deſtructive Infirmities of Nature; and ſo they have died before they attained to that extent of Days which God has allowed unto Mankind, even that Period which ends with old Age, in which through a natural Decay of Strength we are rendred unable any longer to ſubſiſt.</p>
               <p>And thus having gone through what I did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſay on theſe ſeveral Heads, I ſhall conclude by only adding, that the Reaſon of my making this publick to the World is not out of ill-will to any Man's Perſon who does profeſs theſe Doctrines, but out of a Deſire to convince them all of their Error: and that I may expreſs that ſincere Love and juſt Eſteem which I bear to many of this Perſwaſion, who in the Belief of ſo ill a Faith do yet live a ſober good Life; hoping that hereby I may do ſome good to them for whom I have ſo great a Kindneſs, by thus endeavouring to perſwade them not to truſt on ſuch an unſecure Foundation as is that of the Doctrine herein confuted. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all which it may poſſibly be that hereby di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers contending Parties may be induc'd to a more eaſy Reconciliation as to the Matters in difference between them; by which means the Peace and Unity of this Church may be advanced, which at this time is ſo neceſſary in order to the making us better able to reſiſt both the publick and private Enemies of this proteſtant Church and Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:150018:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150018:23"/>
            <head>Books printed for <hi>Richard Cumberland,</hi> at the Angel in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1696.</head>
            <p>THe Government of the Thoughts, a preſatory Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe to the Government of the Tongue. In <hi>Octavo.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reform'd Devotions, in Meditations, Hymns, and Petitions, for every Day in the Week, and every Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in the Year. Divided into two Parts. The fourth Edition. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A brief and plain Expoſition of the Church-Catechiſm, compos'd for the Uſe of a Private Shool; Erected and maintained at the Coſt and Charges of ſeveral Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Perſons belonging to the <hi>New Church</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> By <hi>Thomas Jekyll,</hi> D. D. The ſecond Edition. Price 9 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning friendly Reproof: explaining clearly the Nature, Excellency, and Uſefulneſs of it. Proving both from Reaſon and Revelation, that it is an indiſpenſable Duty: And laying down very plain Rules concerning the propereſt Methods, both of giving and receiving it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Serious Reflections on Time and Eternity; with ſome other Subjects moral and divine. To which is annex'd an <hi>Appendix</hi> concerning <hi>the firſt Day of the Year,</hi> how ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the <hi>Jews,</hi> and may beſt be employed by a ſerious <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> With an Exhortation to Youth to prepare for Judgment. The third Edition certected and very much enlarged. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150018:24"/>
            <p>Sacramental Diſcourſes on ſeveral Texts, before and after the Lord's Supper; with a Paraphraſe upon the Lord's Prayer. The ſecond Edition. Boty by Mr. <hi>John Shower.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Batchelor's Directory:</hi> Being a Treatiſe of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence of Marriage. Of its Neceſſity, and the Means to live happy in it. Together with an Apology for the Women againſt the Calumnies of the Men. The ſecond Edition. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Horological Diſquiſitions concerning the Nature of Time, and the <hi>Reaſons</hi> why all <hi>Days,</hi> from <hi>Noon</hi> to <hi>Noon,</hi> are not alike twenty four Hours long. In which appears the Impoſſibility of a Clock's being always kept exactly true to the Sun. With <hi>Tables</hi> of <hi>Equation,</hi> and newer and better <hi>Rules</hi> than any yet extant; how thereby preciſely to adjuſt <hi>Royal Pendulums,</hi> and keep them afterwards, as near as poſſible to the apparent Time. With a <hi>Table</hi> of <hi>Pendulums,</hi> ſhewing the <hi>Beats</hi> that any Length makes in an Hour. A Work very neceſſary for all that would underſtand the true Way of rightly managing Clocks and Watches. By <hi>John Smith,</hi> C. M. To which are added, The beſt Rules for the Ordering and Uſe both of the <hi>Quick-Silver</hi> and <hi>Spirit Weather-glaſſes:</hi> And Mr. <hi>S. Watſon</hi>'s Rules for adjuſting a Clock by the <hi>Fixed Stars.</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay, for Regulating of the Coin: Wherein alſo is ſet forth, <hi>firſt,</hi> How we have loſt that Import of Plate and Bullion we formerly had. <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is become of the great Quantities of Money coined in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. and the preceding Reigns. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The neceſſity there is at this Time for to rectify the preſent Coin of the Kingdom. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By what Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods the Church of calling in the preſent Money, and bringing it to a deſigned Standard, may be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Whether the Method propoſed for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of our Money (and the Bullion of which it's
<pb facs="tcp:150018:24"/>made) be convenient or inconvenient for the Trade of the Nation. The ſecond Edition, with an additional Propoſition. By <hi>A.<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Propoſal for the Raiſing of the Silver Coin of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> from 60 Pence in the Ounce to 75 Pence, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; with the Conſequences thereof. Price 3<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Lately Publiſhed,</head>
               <p>A Scriptural Catechiſm: Or, <hi>The whole Duty of Man</hi> laid down in expreſs Words of Scripture, chiefly intended for the Benefit of the younger Sort. Divided into two Parts: The firſt containing the chief Principles of our Chriſtian Belief. The ſecond inſtructing us in our Duty to God and Man, according to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod obſerved in the Excellent Book, intituled, <hi>The whole Duty of Man.</hi> To which is added, ſome private Devotions in expreſs Words of Scripture: With devour Collects for ſeveral Occaſions. Recommended by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Edward</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Account of one <hi>Ann Jefferies,</hi> now Living in the County of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> who was fed for ſix Months by a ſmall ſort of Airy People call'd <hi>Fairies.</hi> And of the ſtrange and wonderful Cures ſhe performed with Salves and Medicines ſhe received from them, for which ſhe never took one Penny of her Patients. In a Letter from <hi>Moſes Pitt</hi> to the Right Reverend Father in God Dr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Fowler,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Antidote againſt ſome Principal Errors of the Predeſtinarians. A Work deſigned for the Information of the Common People.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150018:25"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:150018:26"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:150018:26"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
